{"test_questions": [[{"question": "A cordless telephone using separate frequencies for transmission in base and portable units is known as", "opta": "duplex arrangement", "optb": "half duplex arrangement", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Separate frequencies for transmission from base and portable units allows two way transmission and is called duplex arrangement."}, {"question": "For attenuation of high frequencies we should use", "opta": "shunt capacitance", "optb": "series capacitance", "optc": "inductance", "optd": "resistance", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since Xc for high frequencies is low, the high frequencies are shunted to ground and are not transmitted."}, {"question": "A modem is classified as low speed if data rate handled is", "opta": "upto 100 bps", "optb": "upto 250 bps", "optc": "upto 400 bps", "optd": "upto 600 bps", "ans": "D", "explanation": "When data rate in bits per second is upto 600, modem is low speed."}, {"question": "VSB modulation is preferred in TV because", "opta": "it reduces the bandwidth requirement to half", "optb": "it avoids phase distortion at low frequencies", "optc": "it results in better reception", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "VSB (vestigial side band) transmission transmits one side band fully and the other side band partially thus, reducing the bandwidth requirement."}, {"question": "A woofer should be fed from the input through a", "opta": "low pass filter", "optb": "high pass filter", "optc": "band pass filter", "optd": "band stop filter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Woofer is a low frequency loud speaker covering the range 16 Hz to 500 Hz."}, {"question": "The colour subcarrier and sidebands produced by its modulation with the chrominance signals are accommodated in the standard channel width by the process of", "opta": "frequency adjustment", "optb": "frequency interleaving", "optc": "frequency changing", "optd": "frequency amalgamation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In frequency interleaving the space between bundles is used for colour signal."}, {"question": "In FM signal with a modulation index mf is passed through a frequency tripler. The wave in the output of the tripler will have a modulation index of", "opta": "mf", "optb": "3mf", "optc": "mf/3", "optd": "mf/9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency multiplier increase the deviation, \n."}, {"question": "In colour TV receiver, varactor diode is used for", "opta": "detection", "optb": "rectification", "optc": "tuning", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In varactor diode the applied reverse bias controls the width and therefore capacitance of depletion layer. \nThis capacitance is used for tuning."}, {"question": "The number of noise sources in a BJT are", "opta": "3", "optb": "2", "optc": "1", "optd": "4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Shot noise, partition noise and thermal noise."}, {"question": "Energy content of atmospheric noise", "opta": "does not depend on frequency", "optb": "decreases as frequency is increased", "optc": "increases as frequency is increased", "optd": "either (a) or (c) depending on the temperature", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Atmospheric noise decreases as frequency is increased."}, {"question": "A 400 W carrier is amplitude modulated with m = 0.75. The total power in AM is", "opta": "400 W", "optb": "512 W", "optc": "588 W", "optd": "650 W", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "c(t) and m(t) are used to generate an FM signal. If the peak frequency deviation of the generated FM signal is three times the transmission bandwidth of the AM signal, then the coefficient of the term cos [2p(1008 x 103t)] in the FM signal (in terms of the Bessel Coefficients) is", "opta": "5 J4(3)", "optb": "J8(3)", "optc": "J8(4)", "optd": "5 J4(6)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As, we known FM, s(t)\n\n Frequency deviation = 3 . (AM Bandwidth) = 6 fm\n\nand \u03b2= 6 is given in (d) only.\n\u03c9c + n \u03c9m = (1008 x 103)2p \n 2p x 106 + n. 4p x 103 = (1008 x 103).2p \n n = 4\nSo, \u03b2 = 6, n = 4 hence answer is 5j4(6)."}, {"question": "Non-coherently detection is not possible for", "opta": "PSK", "optb": "ASK", "optc": "FSK", "optd": "both (a) and (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tracking of extra terrestrial objects requires", "opta": "high transmitting power", "optb": "very sensitive receiver", "optc": "fully steerable antenna", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All the three are required."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Free space does not interfere with normal radiation and propagation of radio wavesReason (R):  Free space has no magnetic or gravitational fields.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since free space does not have magnetic and other fields, waves can propagate without any interference."}, {"question": "In radar systems PRF stands for", "opta": "Power Return Factor", "optb": "Pulse Return Factor", "optc": "Pulse Repetition Frequency", "optd": "Pulse Response Factor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "PRF in radar systems means pulse repetition frequency."}, {"question": "Which of the following cannot be the Fourier series expansion of a periodic signal?", "opta": "x(t) = 2 cos t + 3 cos 3t", "optb": "x(t) = 2 cos pt + 7 cos t", "optc": "x(t) = cos t + 0.5", "optd": "x(t) = 2 cos 1.5pt + sin 3.5 pt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "x(t) = cos t + 0.5\nnot satisfies the Dirichlet condition. \nThe integration of constant term is \u221e."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the indirect way of FM generation?", "opta": "Reactance bipolar transistor modulator", "optb": "Armstrong modulator", "optc": "Varactor diode modulator", "optd": "Reactance FM modulator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It generates FM through phase modulation."}, {"question": "A telephone exchange has 9000 subscribers. If the number of calls originating at peak time is 10, 000 in one hour, the calling rate is", "opta": "0.9", "optb": "10/9", "optc": "0.81", "optd": "0.1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Calling rate is the number of calls per subscriber."}, {"question": "If C is capacity of noisy channel, (bits/s), \u03b4f is bandwidth Hz and S/N is signal to noise ratio, then", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is Shannon-Hartley theorem."}, {"question": "As the frequency increases, the absorption of ground wave by earth's surface", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remains the same", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because of this reason ground waves can be used for frequencies upto about 1600 kHz only."}, {"question": "The velocity of sound waves in air", "opta": "is constant at all temperatures", "optb": "varies directly as temperature", "optc": "varies inversely as absolute temperature", "optd": "varies directly as square root of absolute temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "v \u221d T."}, {"question": "The range of a cordless telephone is about", "opta": "1000 m", "optb": "500 m", "optc": "100 m", "optd": "10 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The range depends on quality of instrument and is about 100 m."}, {"question": "An earth mat for a communication tower consists of", "opta": "one or two radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 5 cm below ground", "optb": "a large number of radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 3 m", "optc": "a large number of radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 30 cm", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The number of radials is large and depth is about 30 cm."}, {"question": "Degaussing in a picture tube means", "opta": "Adding magnetism in mask and mounting frame", "optb": "Removing residual magnetism in mask, shield etc...", "optc": "Increasing resistance of coils to decrease time constant", "optd": "Decreasing resistance of coils to increase time constant.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since gauss is a unit of magnetic flux, degaussing means removal of magnetism."}, {"question": "The rate at which information can be carried through a communication channel depends on", "opta": "carrier frequency", "optb": "bandwidth", "optc": "transmission loss", "optd": "transmitted power", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Rate of information depends on bandwidth."}, {"question": "Some types of traps used in video IF amplifier of colour TV are", "opta": "shunt traps", "optb": "series traps", "optc": "absorption traps", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All these are used."}, {"question": "Direct and reflected sound waves may interfere with each other.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "PAS use moving coil microphones."}, {"question": "A carrier is simultaneously modulated by two sine waves having modulation indices of 0.4 and 0.3. The total modulation index will be", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "0.7", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0.35", "ans": "C", "explanation": "m1 = 0.4, m2 = 0.3\n."}, {"question": "A 1000 kHz carrier is simultaneously modulated with 300 Hz, 800 Hz and 2 kHz audio sine waves. Which of the following frequency is least likely to be present in the output?", "opta": "1002 kHz", "optb": "1000 kHz", "optc": "999.2 kHz", "optd": "998.0 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency present in the sidebands is equal to = fc \u00b1 fm, fc \u00b1 2fm , fc \u00b1 3fm ."}, {"question": "In standing wave pattern on a transmission line", "opta": "voltage and current nodes coincide", "optb": "voltage and current antinodes coincide", "optc": "voltage nodes and current antinodes as well as current nodes and voltage antinodes coincide", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When standing wave is set up voltage maxima and current minima and voltage minima and current maxima coincide."}, {"question": "If the bandwidth is increased by 2, the \u03b3FM \u03b3AM (where \u03b3 is the ratio of SNR of output to SNR at input, FM is frequency modulation and AM is amplitude modulation) is increased by a factor of", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Doubling of frequency increase SNR in frequency modulation by 4. It has no effect in AM."}, {"question": "In the figure , the output y(t) will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A carrier wave carries information.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Carrier does not have any information."}, {"question": "Frequency shift keying is used mostly in", "opta": "telegraphy", "optb": "telephony", "optc": "satellite communication", "optd": "radio transmission", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Frequency shift keying (FSK) is a system of frequency modulation used in telegraphy."}, {"question": "It is desired that transmission line and load should match for a range of frequencies. The best method is", "opta": "to use a balun", "optb": "to use a single stub of adjustable position", "optc": "to use a double stub", "optd": "to use a broad band amplifier", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When matching over a range of frequencies is desired, double stub is necessary."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the highest input impedance?", "opta": "CE", "optb": "CB", "optc": "CC", "optd": "Push pull", "ans": "C", "explanation": "CC connection has very high input impedance and low output impedance."}, {"question": "In a fascimile reproduction time to scan one line is 2 ms. If it has 4% blanking, the visible trace time is", "opta": "1.92 ms", "optb": "2.08 ms", "optc": "50 ms", "optd": "0.08 ms", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(2 ms) (1 - 0.04) = 1.92 ms."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements The amplitude of an FM wave is constantFM is more immune to noise than AMFM broadcasts operate in upper VHF and UHF frequency rangesFM transmitting and receiving equipments are simpler as compared to AM transmitting and receiving equipments Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "1, 2, 3", "optc": "2, 3, 4", "optd": "1, 3, 4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "FM equipments are complex as compared to AM equipments."}, {"question": "Signal to noise ratio of microphone is defined as the ratio of output when the sound pressure is __________ to the output in the absence of any sound signal.", "opta": "0.5 Pa", "optb": "0.2 Pa", "optc": "0.1 Pa", "optd": "0.01 Pa", "ans": "C", "explanation": "0.1 Pa (= 0.5 x 10-4 W/m2) is taken as standard sound pressure for defining S/N ratio of microphones."}, {"question": "A generator is feeding power to a transmission line of characteristic impedance Z0. The line is terminated in impedance ZL. Standing waves will be set up if", "opta": "ZL = Z0", "optb": "ZL < Z0", "optc": "ZL > Z0", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the case, i.e., ZL > Z0 and ZL < Z0 give rise to standing waves."}, {"question": "In sound recording the degree of pre-emphasis is about 6 dB/ octave.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It erases the matter already existing on the tape."}, {"question": "Space wave may be a direct wave or wave reflected from earth.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Strength of space wave depends on distance as it suffers attenuation."}, {"question": "Radio broadcasts are generally", "opta": "amplitude modulation", "optb": "frequency modulation", "optc": "both amplitude and frequency modulation", "optd": "neither amplitude nor frequency modulation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency modulation gives noise free reception and is used for radio broadcasts."}, {"question": "If the frequency of a wave 20 Hz, the time period is", "opta": "20 secs", "optb": "2 secs", "optc": "0.2 secs", "optd": "0.05 secs", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Which of the following is taken as reference antenna for directive gain?", "opta": "Half wave dipole", "optb": "Elementary doublet", "optc": "Isotropic", "optd": "Infinitesimal dipole", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Isotropic antenna is one which radiates equally in all directions. It is a standard reference antenna."}, {"question": "Push pull amplifier is", "opta": "voltage amplifier", "optb": "current amplifier", "optc": "power amplifier", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Push pull is a power amplifier."}, {"question": "When the channel is noisy, producing a conditional probability of error p = 0.5; the channel capacity and entropy function would be, respectively,", "opta": "1 and 1", "optb": "1 and 0.5", "optc": "0.5 and 1", "optd": "0 and 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In CCIR-B system, the time between start of one H syn. pulse and next is", "opta": "64 \u03bcs", "optb": "6.4 \u03bcs", "optc": "640 \u03bcs", "optd": "0.64 \u03bcs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The frequency of H pulses is 15625 Hz. \nHence ."}, {"question": "Counterpoise is used in coils having", "opta": "high resistivity", "optb": "low resistivity", "optc": "medium resistivity", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Counterpoise is a horizontally buried wire used to provide low grounding resistance in high resistivity soils."}]]}